Ulysses S. Grant III Papers
Ulysses S. Grant III Papers
1850-1937
Grant, U. S. (Ulysses S.), 1881-1968
7 linear ft.
Bulk of collection consists of advertisements, blueprints, bids and other material relating to architectural projects; a few articles on conditions in Russia by Princess Cantacuzene (Julia Dent Grant, sister of Ulysses), including one about her escape from Russia.
2652442
Biographical History
Ulysses S. Grant III (1881-1968) was an American army officer, civil engineer and architect. The grandson of Ulysses S. Grant, 18th President of the United States, he was born on the Fourth of July and attended Cutler School (1895-1897) and Columbia University (1898), both in New York City. He left in 1898 to fight in the Spanish-American War, and in 1899 entered West Point where he was a classmate of Douglas MacArthur. In 1907 he married Edith Root, daughter of Elihu Root, Roosevelt's secretary of state.
As a member of the Army Corps of Engineers, he served in the Philippines, Cuba, and Mexico. In 1918 he served as secretary of the American section of the Supreme War Council in Paris (for which he received a Distinguished Service Medal). After the war he was assigned to various engineering commands in the United States, eventually becoming Director of Public Buildings and Parks for Washington, D.C. (1926-1933). By 1942 he had advanced to the rank of Brigadier General; from 1942-1944 he was Chief of the Office of Civilian Defense, protection branch. He retired in 1945 with the rank of Major General, and shortly thereafter became president of George Washington University (1946-1951).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ulysses S. Grant III Papers consists primarily of advertisements, blueprints, bids and other material relating to architectural projects. Other material of interest, although unexpected in this technical collection, is a series of articles on the Russian political situation from the Saturday Evening Post (1918-1919) by Princess Cantacuzene (Julia Dent Grant, sister of Ulysses) A news story from 1920 mentions briefly her escape from Russia. Although the date range for this collection is 1850-1937, the bulk is the period of Grant's service as Director of Public Buildings and Parks in Washington, D. C., 1926-1933.
Arrangement of the Collection
Save for miscellaneous printed materials at the end of the collection, everything has been placed in a single alphabetical run, to include public projects, articles and speeches, notes, and court cases. Within each project, items are listed in chronological order (advertisements for bid, then contracts, then blueprints, finally other material).
Related Material
has a substantial number of architectural collections, both of firms and individuals. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Architects; Grant, U. S. (Ulysses S.), 1881-1968.; United States. -- Army. -- Corps of Engineers.; Civil engineering -- Contracts and specifications.; Civil engineering -- United States.; Civil engineering -- United States -- California.; Civil engineering -- United States -- Washington (D.C.); Civil engineers -- United States.; Military engineering -- Philippines.; Military engineers -- United States.; Public works -- Washington (D.C.); Russia -- Politics and government -- 1917-1936.; Advertisements.; Contracts.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Civil engineers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. John Dietz, 1982.
Inventory
- Architectural materials
  - American River, California
    - "Report to the Federal Power Commission on the uses of American River," for California Power Board, 1924; typescript and printed copies (Box 1)
  - Arlington Memorial Bridge Commission, Washington, D. C. McKim Mead and White, Architects, W. J. Douglas, Consulting Engineer
    - Advertisement, proposals for constructing piers and abutments, Nov. 19, 1925 (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contracts 3 & 4 (furnish and deliver granite), March 22, 1926 (Box 1)
    - Blueprints, contracts 3 & 4, 8 pieces (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contract 16 (superstructure and foundations), Oct. 10, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Blueprints, contract 16, 12 pieces (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contract 22 (bascule draw span), June 15, 1928 (Box 1)
      See also Phoenix Bridge Co. vs. U. S. (Box 4)
    - Advertisement, contract 23 (granite, boundary bridge channel), June 25, 1928 (Box 1)
    - Blueprints, contract 23, 2 pieces (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contract 24 (boundary channel bridge), Sept. 1, 1928 (Box 1)
    - Blueprints, contract 24, 7 pieces (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contract 28 (foundations, bridge plaza, water gate), March 25, 1929 (Box 1)
      See also Grier-Lowrance Construction Co. vs. U. S. (Box 4)
    - Blueprints, contract 28 (Box 1)
    - Transcript, contract 28, daily progress reports (Box 1)
    - Field log entries, contract 28 (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contract 31-33 (granite for bridge plaza, approach structure), June 1, 1929 (Box 1)
    - Blueprints, contract 31-33, 13 pieces (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contract 34 (superstructure, bridge plaza, water gate), Aug. 1, 1929 (Box 1)
    - Blueprints, contract 34, 4 pieces (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contract 40 and 41 (granite carving), March 1, 1930 (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contract 43 (elm trees), May 7, 1930 (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contract 44 (fenders for Bascule draw span) July 2, 1980, 6 pieces (Box 1)
    - Blueprints, contract 44 (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contract 46 (grading parkway to Memorial Entrance to Cemetery), Sept. 8, 1930 (Box 1)
    - Blueprints, contract 46, 4 pieces (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contract 48 (granite for pedestals), Dec. 6, 1930 (Box 1)
    - Blueprints, contract 48 (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contracts 49-52 (granite for memorial entrance to cemetery), Feb. 2, 1931 (Box 1)
    - Blueprints, contracts 49-52, 9 pieces (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contract 53 (grading west end of project), March 16, 1931 (Box 1)
    - Blueprints, contract 53, 1 piece (Box 1)
    - Advertisement, contract 55 (tunnel under parkway to cemetery), March 16, 1931 (Box 2)
    - Blueprints, contract 55, 4 pieces (Box 2)
    - Advertisement, contract 56 (bridge plaza drainage), April 15, 1931 (Box 2)
    - Blueprints, contract 56, 2 pieces (Box 2)
    - Advertisement, contract 57 and 58 (equestrian groups on plaza) no date (Box 2)
    - Advertisement, contract 62 (paving Arlington Memorial Bridge & Boundary Channel Bridge), August 15, 1931 (Box 2)
    - Blueprints, contract 62, 1 piece (Box 2)
    - Advertisement, contract 63 (paving curb, sidewalks, etc., for bridge plaza), Sept. 3, 1931 (Box 2)
    - Blueprints, contract 63, 8 pieces (Box 2)
    - Advertisement, contract 65 (asphalt penetration macadam paving on Columbia Island), Oct. 19, 1931 (Box 2)
    - Blueprints, contract 69, 4 pieces (Box 2)
    - Advertisement, contract 75 (reinforced concrete pavement, etc., Memorial Ave. to cemetery), August 2, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Advertisement, contract 70-72 (ornamental evergreens), Jan. 18, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Blueprints, contract 70-72, 3 pieces (Box 2)
    - Advertisement, contract 73 (pavement, etc. on road to Ericsson Memorial), Feb. 23, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Blueprints, contract 73, 2 pieces (Box 2)
    - Advertisement, contract 74 (temporary gravel surface, Memorial Ave. to cemetery), Feb. 13, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Blueprints, contract 74, 1 piece (Box 2)
    - Blueprints, contract 75, 7 pieces (Box 2)
    - Advertisement, contract 76 (transplanting elm trees, east end of bridge), March 9, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Blueprints, contract 76, 1 piece (Box 2)
    - Advertisement, contract 78 (Memorial entrance to Arlington National Cemetery), April 11, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Blueprints, contract 78, 18 pieces (Box 2)
    - Advertisement, transplant white pine and American elm, Dec. 7, 1931 (Box 2)
    - Specifications for carving frescoes, Nov. 21, 1927 (Box 2)
    - Specifications, and blueprints for Keystone carving, Nov. 14, 1927 (Box 2)
    - Contract drawings, contracts 1, 16, 22, 24, 34, 2 copies (Oversize 1)
  - Articles, speeches, etc., 1925-1932 (Box 2)
  - Astronomy
    - Program for field, 1906-1907 (Box 2)
    - Azimuth observations (Box 2)
    - Latitude by sextant (Box 2)
    - Latitude by zenith telescope (Box 2)
    - Latitude, transit in prime vertical (Box 2)
    - Time, by sextant (Box 2)
    - Time, transit in the meridian, chronograph method (Box 2)
    - Time, transit in the meridian, eye and ear method (Box 2)
  - Breakwater, Gloucester, Mass., 1 pg., costs and measurements (Box 2)
  - Calaveras River, California, flood control, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Civil engineering
    - Building construction, ventilating, heating, roofs and bridges (Box 2)
    - Cement, masonry, concretes, foundations (Box 2)
    - Hydraulics, river and harbor improvements, lock gates (Box 2)
    - Water supply and sewage disposal (Box 2)
    - [Civilian engineers and the military], 1921 (Box 2)
  - Dam across Suison Bay, California, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Drydocks; Gonzalez, Teodomino, correspondence, etc (Box 2)
  - East Potomac Park, Washington, D. C., Tourist Camp Field House
    - Advertisement for bids, May 21, 1926 (Box 2)
    - Blueprints, 9 pieces (Box 2)
  - Feather River, California
    - Survey recommendations, Feb., 1923 (Box 3)
    - Survey report, May, 1925 (Box 3)
    - Maps, index, sheets 1-7 (Box 3)
    - Maps, sheets 8-13, 2 copies of sheet 13 (Box 3)
    - Maps, profile and cross-sections, sheets 1-4 (Box 3)
  - Federal Warehouse, Washington, D. C. William T. Partridge, Consulting Architect, Lockwood Greene Engineers, Inc., Consulting Engineers
    - Advertisement for bids, July 31, 1931 (Box 3)
    - Blueprints, location plan, survey of site, 2 pieces (Box 3)
    - Blueprints, 1st-7th floors, basement, roof, 6 pieces (Box 3)
    - Blueprints, elevations, N/S and E/W, 2 pieces (Box 3)
    - Blueprints, sections through building, plumbing section, 2 pieces (Box 3)
    - Blueprints, architectural details, 3 pieces (Box 3)
    - Blueprints, structural, 2 folders, 11 pieces (Box 3)
    - Blueprints, heating and ventilation, 5 pieces (Box 3)
    - Blueprints, electrical, 4 pieces (Box 3)
    - Blueprints, sprinkler system, 4 pieces (Box 4)
    - Blueprints, vacuum cleaning system, 1 piece (Box 4)
  - Francis Junior High School, Washington, D. C., Bath house and pools. Thomas M. Medford, Architect, W. B. Montgomery, Structural engineer, E. A. Hind, Mechanical engineer
    - Advertisement, bid, ca. Jan. 1928 (Box 4)
    - Blueprints, 17 pieces (Box 4)
  - Grier-Lowrance Construction Co., Inc. vs. United States, 1931-1937; 2 folders (Box 4)
    See also Arlington Memorial Bridge, contract 28, foundations (Box 1)
  - Industrial mobilization speech, 1925 (Box 4)
  - Lights [intensity of various illuminants data] and printed material, 1908-1926 (Box 4)
  - Locks and canals in the U. S. not owned by the government, April-May, 1904; table, 6 sheets (Box 4)
  - Locks for rivers and canals
    - Examples, Sept 21, 1910; text and 4 sheets (Box 4)
    - Moline, Illinois, Mar. 1912 (Box 4)
    - Lock no. 6, Warrior River, Alabama, Aug. 1911; text and 5 drawings (Box 4)
    - Illinois and Mississippi Canal, Illinois, June 1912; text and 4 drawings (Box 4)
  - McKinley High School, Washington, D. C., bathhouse and pools. Thomas M. Medford, Architect, W. B. Montgomery, Structural Engineer, E. A. Hind, Mechanical Engineer
    - Advertisement, bid, July 25, 1927 (Box 4)
    - Amendment, Aug. 8, 1927 (Box 4)
    - Blueprints, location plat, electrical, plumbing, 6 pieces (Box 4)
    - Blueprints, details, 2 folders, 24 pieces (Box 4)
  - Military engineering
    - Defense of Subic Bay, Philippines, 1906; text, diagram map (Box 4)
    - Strategy, naval and coastal defense, undated (Box 4)
  - Mining Convention/Conference, on federal control of hydraulic mining for gold, 1923 (Box 4)
  - Phoenix Bridge Co. vs. United States, 1937 (Box 4)
    See also Arlington Memorial Bridge, contract 22, Bascule draw span (Box 1)
  - Rock Creek and Potomac Parkway, Washington, D. C
    - "L" Street Bridge. D. H. Gillette, Chief, Engineering Div., John L. Nagle, Chief, Design Sect
      - Advertisement, bids, Dec. 7, 1931; Sept. 16, 1932 (Box 4)
      - Blueprints, 6 pieces (Box 4)
    - Lyons Mill Bridge. D. H. Gillette, Chief, Engineering Div., John L. Nagle, Chief, Design Sect
      - Blueprints, 4 pieces (Box 4)
    - Waterside Drive Overpass. D. H. Gillette, Chief, Engineering Div., John L Nagle, Chief, Design Sect
      - Advertisement bid, April 24, 1931 (Box 4)
      - Blueprints, 11 pieces (Box 4)
  - Rock Creek Park, Washington, D. C
    - Milkhouse Ford Bridge blueprints, 1925; 3 pieces (Box 5)
    - Grapevine Bridge blueprints, 1928; 2 pieces (Box 5)
  - Sacramento River, California
    - Survey, Sacramento to Collinsville, 1924; text and 5 blueprints (Box 5)
  - Sacramento River Flood Control Project
    - 1925, text and maps (Box 5)
    - Revision report, 1925; text and maps; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Sacramento, San Joaquin Rivers, California
    - Notes and speeches, 1920-1924 (Box 5)
    - Report of preliminary examination and survey, 1924 (Box 5)
    - Physical description, commercial estimate, 1920 (Box 5)
    - Flood control, 1925-1927 (Box 5)
  - San Joaquin River
    - Bridge above Antioch, application for, ca. 1925 (Box 5)
    - Fresno County, California, power development, 1924 (Box 5)
  - Seacoast fortification, tests of parapets, Sandy Hook, New Jersey, Dec., 1918 (Box 5)
  - Severn et al vs. United States, 1936-1937 (Box 5)
  - Staniaus River, California, report to the Federal Power Commission on use, 1924 (Box 5)
  - Stockton, California, Deep waterway, 1922-1924; includes report of survey; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Trinity River, California
    - Report to the Federal Power Commission on uses, 1924 (Box 5)
    - Waterflow, 1902; notes (Box 5)
  - White House, Washington, D. C
    - Rebuilding of roof, 3rd and 2nd floor ceilings
      - Advertisement, bid, Nov. 19, 1926 (Box 5)
      - Blueprints, work in place, ground floor, 1st and 2nd floor, 3 pieces (Box 5)
      - Blueprints, ground floor, 2nd & 3rd floors, 6 pieces (Box 5)
      - Blueprints, attic, roof and west terrace, 3 pieces (Box 5)
      - Blueprints, transverse and longitudinal sections, 2 pieces (Box 5)
      - Blueprints, exterior elevations, 4 pieces (Box 5)
      - Blueprints, interior elevations, 4 pieces (Box 5)
      - Blueprints, roof framing, 3rd floor framing, 3 pieces (Box 6)
      - Blueprints, details, 6 pieces (Box 6)
      - Blueprints, mechanical and truss detail, 2 pieces (Box 6)
    - Swimming pool, West terrace. Lorenzo S. Winslow, Architect, John L. Nagle, Chief, Engineering Div., D. H. Gillette, Chief, Design sect
      - Advertisements, bid, April 5, 1933 (Box 6)
      - Blueprints, 6 pieces (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous printed material on flood control, military engineering, evaluation of building materials, sewage, harbors, etc., 1850-1932 (Box 6)
- Clippings
  - Cantacuzene, Princess (Julia Dent Grant), 1918-1919; printed material; on Russia (Oversize 1)